Finding Aid for the Robert A. Baldwin Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Robert A. Baldwin Collection
1953-2004
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0583
3 linear feet
Biography/History
Robert A. Baldwin was born in 1930 in Bridgeport, Connecticut, and later moved to Andover, Massachusetts. In 1952, he received a Bachelor of Arts in English Literature and in Fine Arts from Oberlin College. In 1955, he received a Masters of Fine Arts from Yale University concentrating in scene, costume and lighting design.
He served in the U.S. Army from 1955-1957 as Designer-Technical Director, U. S. Army Entertainment Program in Stuttgart, Germany. He was employed by Vanderbilt University from 1957 until his retirement in 1995. During his tenure, he held many titles including Instructor in Drama, Assistant/Associate Professor of Drama, Planner for the Office of Campus Planning, Associate Professor of Drama and University Centennial Coordinator, Associate Professor Fine Arts and Assistant to the Dean for the College of Arts and Science. He was also the Associate Professor of Theatre and Associate Professor of Fine Arts (Joint Appointment) from 1983 until his retirement. He was awarded The Chancellor’s Cup in 1987, and in 1995 became Professor of Fine Arts Emeritus and Professor Theatre Emeritus.
Professor Baldwin donated his collection to Special Collections in 2004. A selection of images will be displayed, with the remaining images available in the department for viewing.
Scope and Contents
The 3 linear feet collection contains 28 designs of stage scenery from various play productions created over a 30-year period. The stage scenery designs have been professionally matted. There are also 17 costume designs for men, women and/or groups from various time periods. A CD-ROM of all designs is included. The collection is stored in five flat boxes.
- Costume Designs – Series of 14 drawings
  - Roman Man, 100 BC (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - English Man, 1346 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - English Woman, 1588 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - French Woman, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - French Woman, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - English Man, End of 14th Century (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - English Woman, 1360 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - English Woman, 1380 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - English Man, 1542 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - English Man, 1560-70 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - French Woman, 1445-60 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - French Man, 1655 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - French Man, 1635 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - French Man, 1680 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Costume Designs – Series of 3 drawings
  - Costume Project - Saint Joan – Scene I – Vaucouleurs, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Costume Project – Saint Joan – Scene II – Chinon (1st Plate), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Costume Project – Saint Joan – Scene II – Chinon (2nd Plate), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Stage Scenery Designs
  - “The Wind of Heaven”
    - by Emlyn Williams, 1953
    - Yale Drama School Production
  - “Key Largo”, Act I (Box 2)
    - by Maxwell Anderson, 1953
    - Yale Drama School Production
  - “Key Largo”, Act II (Box 2)
    - by Maxwell Anderson, 1953
    - Yale Drama School Production
  - “The Green Bay Tree” (Box 2)
    - by Louis Bromfield, 1954
    - Yale Assignment
  - “Ring Around the Moon” (Box 2)
    - by Jean Anouilh, 1954
    - Design for Elmhurst College
  - “Major Barbara”, Act II (Box 2)
    - by G. B. Shaw, 1954
    - Yale Drama School, Major Production
  - “Major Barbara”, Act III (Box 2)
    - by G. B. Shaw, 1954
    - Yale Drama School, Major Production
- Stage Scenery Designs [Yale Thesis]
  - “The Oresteia”, Eumenides Portal (Box 3)
    - by Aeschylus, 1955
  - “The Oresteia”, The House of Atreus (Box 3)
    - by Aeschylus, 1955
  - “The Oresteia”, The Tomb of Agamemnon (Box 3)
    - by Aeschylus, 1955
  - “The Oresteia”, Temple of Apollo (Box 3)
    - by Aeschylus, 1955
  - “The Oresteia”, The Shrine of Athena (Box 3)
    - by Aeschylus, 1955
- Stage Scenery Designs
  - “Arsenic and Old Lace” (Box 4)
    - by J. Kesselring, 1957
  - “The Marching Song” (Box 4)
    - by John Whiting, 1958
    - A Chamber Theatre Production
  - “The Miser” (Box 4)
    - by Moliere, 1958
  - “The Love of Four Colonels”, French Scene
    - by Peter Ustinov, 1959
    - A Chamber Theatre Production
  - “Androcles and the Lion” (Box 4)
    - by G. B. Shaw, 1959
  - “I Choose to Die”, Act I (Box 4)
    - by Brainard Cheney, 1960
  - “I Choose to Die, Prison”, Act II (Box 4)
    - by Brainard Cheney, 1960
- Stage Scenery Designs
  - “The Waltz of the Toreadors” (Box 5)
    - by Jean Anouilh, 1963
  - “The Government Inspector”, Act I (Box 5)
    - by Nicholai Gogol, 1963
  - “The Government Inspector”, Act II
    - by Nicholai Gogol, 1963
  - “The Late George Apley” (Box 5)
    - by Marguand and Kaufman, 1966
  - “Dr. Faustus”, Faustus Study (Box 5)
    - by Christoph Marlowe, [1970]
  - “Dr. Faustus”, Faust Conjuring up the Devil (Box 5)
    - by Christoph Marlowe, [1970]
  - “Dr. Faustus”, Faustus Last Hour, Waiting for Damnation (Box 5)
    - by Christoph Marlowe, [1970]
  - “Saint Joan”, Act One (Box 5)
    - by G. B. Shaw, 1984 - unproduced project
  - “Saint Joan”, Court (Box 5)
    - by G. B. Shaw, 1984 - unproduced project
- Photograph – (1)
  - Baldwin, Robert A. – 4” x 6” color image, [2004]
- Vita – (1)
  - Baldwin, Robert A.